We will crack into it, given our time constraints.
So back to our public submissions on the Conservation
Amendment Bill. Welcome to Simpson Grierson this
afternoon. You have 15 minutes with us, so take your submission as read,
but we'll hand it over to you for your opening remarks and then open up for
questions. So thank you.
Thank you, Madam Chair. Sally McKechnie, Hamish Harwood.
We're delighted to be here this afternoon.
As I said before, we formally commenced.
Ours is a very targeted submission.
We are
public lawyers,
both of us, and the practice that the firm has is very much focused on
assisting clients engaging with the department.
So we have focused our submission on those procedural,
structural matters rather than some of the other elements of the bill, which
you may be receiving
the majority of the submissions in relation to.
Mm.
So there's four primary submissions
that we've highlighted, and we'll speak to three of those, particularly today.
I'll speak to the first two,
the statutory timeframes and the mechanisms to
facilitate the use of AI, and then Hamish will speak particularly
to the conservation policy statement.
Hamish is a resource management practitioner and has considerable
experience in that area as well.
So turning to the statutory timeframes, committee, we strongly
support
the introduction of those timeframes into the bill.
And
there it is, a significant issue that our clients often wrestle with, the
black box of the department. We are aware, of course, that there are
internal timeframes and deadlines, but it is quite mysterious
to applicants often what is happening, how long it will take to happen, and the
like. And so that public accountability of a timeframe we strongly
encourage.
Mysterious.
We do make a recommendation, committee, for your consideration that there is public
accounting
at a
high level of timeframes and extensions.
We acknowledge that there's intended to be no mechanism of accountability if
timeframes are extended, and we consider that to be appropriate.
There are reasons why timeframes may need to be extended.
But to enhance public accountability and visibility of
those, we are making a suggestion in our submission that there is a
requirement to report to the minister
and that that report is made public with the intention that it highlights if there
are systemic trends or issues that need to be resolved, and
hopefully to create an improvement loop over time,
to assess why these are
being required and be able to be resolved.
Secondly, there is a consideration, which again, we support,
that the less controversial permits and
concessions currently being dealt with by the Department of Conservation move to a
more automated basis.
There is a very wide range, perhaps too wide a range of material
currently going through the department.
But if it is possible to make the uncontroversial
more streamlined, we would support that.
But we do note that at present, and this is not unique to the bill, it's across
much of the statutory book, there is not a
mechanism to authorize AI involvement in decision-making.
And we think there probably is a role here for AI to be
used to at least assist human decision-making, particularly in these less
controversial permits, which are a necessity, but
are not,
frankly, difficult.
We would encourage the committee to consider
allowing and expressly authorizing the use of AI in
appropriate circumstances. Without that, if it is used,
it creates a risk of challenge to a decision where there doesn't need to be a risk.
In fact, more generally, we would encourage
the government and Parliament to consider an authorization of
AI and public decision-making regime, which goes beyond the
scope of this particular bill, so I won't spend any time on it, but it is one of my
personal hobby horses and is acknowledged, akin to the Privacy Act, if you
will. High level principles for accountability and transparency.
Smart.
But specifically here, we ask, committee, that you consider
authorization
legislation, even if the detail of it sits in regulation
subsequently.
Interesting.
I'll just briefly touch on our third recommendation before turning to the
national policy statement. At the heart of our third
recommendation is really around the unconstrained nature of the scope
of the power to pass on third-party costs
to applicants.
And you would have seen as you read our
submission, that we make some suggestions to
put some guardrails around that power so that costs that are passed on are actual,
reasonable, and proportionate,
things like that.
Our fourth recommendation relates to the-
The new national policy statement framework, which we are
supportive of. But our concern is
the inclusion of a power
in
Schedule 1 that would enable the first
of these documents to be produced without following the
process in Schedule 2.
And our concern with that is really
twofold. And the first is,
we think it's sensible to obviously follow good process and have
a robust
consultation process and development of that initial
document. But also, we think it is efficient
to do,
essentially do the job once well, rather than have a
quick process that produces a statement that might have
some flaws or issues that would've been picked up had you followed the Schedule 2
process in the first instance. That's going to be more efficient overall.
Mm-hmm.
And so we suggest that the first
iteration of this document either goes through the Schedule 2 process or something
like it to ensure that the product is fit for purpose and
as robust as it could be. And
experience would suggest that some of these policy statements are long-lived.
The New Zealand Coastal Policy Statement has been around since 2010.
So it is worth getting them right.
Mm.
You were going to get that one right.
Brilliant. Thank you.
That's it. Brilliant. Thank you.
Yep.
We've got the first question from Rachel Brockie.
Couple of questions.
Mm-hmm.
So the recommendation for, this is just a clarification.
When you say to a minimum procedural safeguards, you're meaning
that at least there is a robust process, not
that the procedural safeguards are minimal.
I think that's your point, Hamish?
Yes. Yeah.
Yeah.
I think that's right. Absolutely.
Just when you read it, the first time I read it, I was like, "Huh?
What?" But no, that makes sense.
Yep.
That's good.
Going to the time frames, which you mention at one
and three.
Well,
I say you mentioned them at one and three because I'm about to bring up funding of
the Department of Conservation, which of course has been depleted
year after year, and so
some of the time frames that you were talking about, part of the reason might
be funding. And then, assuming that to be true,
how does that interact with your recommendation three, which looks
like you're trying to
further reduce funding
that would go to DOC?
Not trying to necessarily understand the first question, Rachel, but the third
recommendation is not to reduce the funding, but just to be clear about what it
will be in advance. Most of our clients are coming at this with relatively
complex applications, and they are happy
to be involved in a user-pays process.
Mm.
They would want to know what is happening as a quid pro quo for user pays,
particularly from a timeframe perspective.
Okay, so it's not to reduce the user pays.
It's just about the transparency of what that money's being used for.
Yes, and to have a sense of it in advance.
You'll have seen in the media recently, in the context of fast track, which of
course is purely user pays, some of the very significant hours that the Department
of Conservation have spent.
Mm.
And at present, there isn't that clarity of mechanism
beyond, "I've spent X number of hours." Like, well, doing what?
So putting some guardrails around it in advance rather than making it a
more open-ended process, which some of the fast track experience
has highlighted how many hours that may in fact be.
Yeah.
Which isn't necessarily problematical, but it means, I think, some transparency
about what.
And so that fits with your first point, your first submission
around the timing and to have clear
time frames, but to not punish DOC if they go over them.
That's your submission?
Yeah. The recommendation with regards to
public transparency is to try and identify what the systemic issues are.
And it may be that there will always be four or five, say,
applications a year, which are so complex they need to be extended.
But if there are some that are being extended because there's an insufficient
number of herpetologists in New Zealand, or there is an issue with
insufficient
rangers in a particular conservancy, which is creating a systemic problem, that's
the intention of it.
Rather than, because it's not a public process beyond an OIA
application, there is no public awareness or applicant awareness of
the experience of others.
Yeah. Understood. Yeah, and I've just got a supplementary on-
Yeah, just following on from the...
So it kind of feeds
Rachel's concern about the funding, and therefore the potential impact that may
have on timeliness.
You could actually say, well, if you get the AI system right,
that might help alleviate with the timeliness because it could take out some of
the
human element, and therefore you reuse the resource.
With your focus on AI, you think there's a potential for that to-
That certainly, I think there is a potential for the less controversial.
Yeah. That's what I mean. Just a-
At present, the range of permits and concessions that need to be addressed
under the Conservation Act is myriad and surprisingly wide.
Yes.
There is a significant volume, particularly for research
and non-commercial
access arrangements, concessions, and the like, which
may well be able to be used. We do see automated decision-making
across our Crown and wider Crown entity clients.
Mm-hmm.
And it works well, and there is a human element involved in it,
but it does make the process much more efficient.
Our concern is some of these applications are controversial.
Yep.
Right? And so we would want to make sure it was appropriately optimized.
Mm.
Thank you.
And Ingrid has a supplementary, too.
Yeah, just on the determination of what is or isn't controversial and
what you said around making decisions once in Schedule 2, doing
them properly, and then using AI. Given what happened
last week with the benefit-
Debacle, not once, but twice, and the government was warned
about that actually using urgency.
How do you determine what is going to be controversial, and are you confident
that that system can actually avoid making the types of mistakes we've seen
recently through rushed legislation?
The department currently does that, Ingrid, in terms of the complexity of
application. So it has a staggered process for fees, for example,
based on complexity.
It's a non-statutory process. It's an internal process for the department,
and you'd need to ask the department if they mischaracterize very often.
But there is currently a triaging process coming in because you do pay
scaled fees.
So I don't think that is necessarily a controversial element of the
department's current process, and we're not suggesting that AI is used for the more
complex applications. But it can create efficiencies in the more run-of-the-mill
applications. To be honest, most of them are not ones that our clients make.
No.
But our clients would be grateful that they could have more focus from the
department's resources on their applications, because the simpler applications
are dealt with more promptly.
Yeah, that's a good point. Ryan also has a supplementary on this.
Thanks, Sally. Your
submission's really clear in terms of manual public reporting annually, in
terms of transparency and I guess accountability.
Are you aware of any other
statutory accountability mechanisms in other departments
whereby just publishing it may not be enough to change behavior?
Is there anything else that could be done to strengthen it as well as publishing?
There have been mechanisms used
in other processes in terms of internal,
almost like a sort of internal arbiter or internal referral if there is an
issue with a matter getting
logged in.
Off the top of my head, Ryan, they're typically more bespoke.
I think the Rugby World Cup agency had a sort of speedy
decision-making mechanism internally, so a sort of internal arbiter for
decision-making.
Right.
Given the volume of applications, that might not be practical because they may get
bombarded on the first day with everybody who's been waiting.
But more at the tail end if there's a refinement at the...
Our recommendation would be that the time frames themselves are an excellent
reform, and that they should be given time to bed in.
And this transparency in reporting, even if it's just
to the minister, but ideally in public, will allow refinement over the
next year or two to see if those mechanisms are assisting.
And if that is insufficient, then further may be done.
But I think that at the moment, there is such a lack of knowledge
outside the department, I can't obviously speak to what the department knows for
themselves,
that just understanding the choke points and difficulties would be a huge step
forward.
Thank you.
Look, thank you very much for your submission today, and obviously a different
perspective from what we've heard.
Obviously, a legal perspective too, and how operationally it could work better
as well is really useful. So really appreciate your time today.
So thank you.
Yeah.
Thank you.
And you didn't have to come far.
Sorry?
You didn't have to come far.
No.
Unlike the next submitters.
Yes. No, not far at all by comparison with Queenstown.
There is a sad lack of skiing in my weekends, however, which I suspect is not
Yes, yeah.
Snow in Wellington sometimes.
Yeah, just the one.
Yes. Look, welcome to the select committee.
We've got Trojan Holdings Limited with us.
And have you got someone joining online as well today?
No, I don't believe so.
No, just yourself. Okay, brilliant. That's good.
You have 15 minutes with us, so we'll hand over to you to open up, and then we'll
open up the questions. Thank you.
Thank you, Madam Chair. Kia ora, my name is Paul Anderson.
I'm director of Trojan Holdings, which is a Queenstown based
business owned by the local Davies family.
Trojan owns and operates a diverse range of businesses,
many of which are located on public conservation land.
You may be familiar with some of the businesses we operate, NZ Ski,
Coronet Peak and The Remarkables, and Mount Hutt, Ultimate Hikes, the Milford and
Routeburn Guided Walks, the Hermitage in Aoraki Mount Cook
Alpine Village, Coast to Coast, KJET, and Bungee New Zealand.
We pay more than $7 million in concession fees to
DOC annually.
Oh, so nice.
Which we understand to be around 28% of the total concession
fees collected by the Crown each year.
Our founder and chairman, Sir John Davies, served as Mayor of the
Queenstown Borough in the mid-1980s, then went on to be the first Mayor of
Queenstown Lakes District Council following amalgamation, and he also served on the
New Zealand Conservation Authority until 1999.
Through Trojan's tourism interests, Sir John
has been a long time operator on public conservation land.
He has promoted a model whereby high-value tourism
experiences help fund and support environmental
protection, and visitor infrastructure, and iconic conservation
areas. This philosophy underpins Trojan's tourism
activities on public conservation land.
Our businesses safely host more than 200,000 individual visitors on
conservation land each year,
and 2,200 tourism
employees work hard to build visitor
appreciation of the places that we operate.
We care deeply about the role we play in looking after our visitors,
caring for the conservation estate, caring for our staff,
and contributing to the communities in which we operate.
Trojan supports the simplification of the conservation management
framework offered by the Conservation Amendment Bill.
Our key message for you is that increased certainty for
businesses operating on conservation land will lead to
increased returns for the Crown to reinvest in that
land.
Conservation statutory documents and legislation have been cumbersome and
difficult to navigate for years. All of the ministers
that we have worked with over the years, ministers of conservation that we've
worked with over the years, have wanted to implement reforms.
We're pleased that this has now progressed and congratulate the current minister
for getting this to this stage.
The main problem with the existing framework is the varying levels of
regulation, which have not been regularly updated.
This means that inconsistencies and conflicts arise between legislation
and other statutory documents. Consequently, the consideration of
concession permissions or amendments are challenging for DOC to
process, and that causes very long processing
timeframes. In turn, that creates
uncertainty, curtails required investment in facilities
on conservation land, and lowers the fees that the Crown could earn and
reinvest in the conservation estate.
I'd just like to bring
a couple of key points from our submission to your attention.
Firstly, as I've said, the bill streamlining uncertainty
reforms should be retained.
The current planning system is too slow, complex, and
inconsistent,
and businesses investing significant capital on conservation land need clearer
rules, faster decision-making, and greater certainty that
is offered by this amendment bill.
Next, we support the explicit recognition of
responsible economic activity on conservation land.
The bill should retain the recognition that conservation outcomes
and responsible economic activity can and should
coexist, and that concessionaires bring capital,
capability, employment, and wider economic benefits to New
Zealand.
First and foremost, we're pleased that the extensive environmental
protection for conservation land are retained,
and that should remain the foundation of the Conservation Act.
The proposed amendment to recognize economic opportunities on
conservation land is sensible and transparent.
It provides more straightforward direction to DOC and will help
position responsible tourism as supporting conservation outcomes,
local communities, and regional economies.
Third, major private investments.
We need to protect major private investments through concession and
allocation settings. Businesses such as ski fields,
accommodation, transport infrastructure, and other capital intensive activity
require long-term tenure confidence.
Without tenure, future investment is discouraged, visitor
experience is compromised, and the amount of funding available for
conservation purposes is reduced.
We've suggested a number of improvements in this point, but in particular, we
suggest to make it explicit that conservation activities involving
significant private capital investment may be exempt from
allocation processes where prescribed criteria are
met.
We also suggest that those allocation criteria are
prescribed in the bill rather than leaving that core assessment matter to
policy or administrative decision.
Next, we support the proposal for tourism access levy framework
targeted at international visitors subject to several suggested
improvements. Public and visitor support for that levy will
depend on fairness, transparency, and visible reinvestment in the
places where the money's collected.
Our suggested improvements include ensuring that visitors are not charged more than
once for the places they visit, and not forcing
concessionaires to collect those fees on behalf of the Crown.
One final point.
We believe that making the National Conservation Policy Statement
and area plans the primary place for strategic
decision making is the right decision.
Strategic issues should be resolved up front in those planning documents,
reducing delays and uncertainty during individual concession
processes while still protecting conservation and visitor
values. In particular, that is the right
place to focus iwi engagement and consultation on those
higher order planning documents, so we all understand where we
stand, and we can work with iwi to
deliver successful conservation outcomes.
We also suggest making an adjustment to the area plans to
include activity limits where necessary and justified to
manage visitor use, protect national, natural, and cultural
values, or maintain visitor experiences.
Thanks for the opportunity to address you today.
I wish you well in your deliberations, and I'm very happy to take any questions.
Thank you, Paul.
Appreciate all the points you've made.
Really interesting. Look, we will go to Rachel Brooking first for a question.
Thanks, Paul.
All right.
Two quick questions and then a more substantive question.
One is just on your-
Three.
They're just little ones.
Well.
Always little.
Always little. These ones are little.
Just the private capital that you talked about.
Yeah.
What sort of number are you imagining there?
I think it'd be somewhere 10 to 20 million.
I think it needs to be substantial,
and in terms of those criteria, where there's a stranded, let's
call it a stranded asset. So obviously our ski fields, the lifts, you can't put
them up and take them somewhere else.
Mm.
Hotel, the Hermitage at Mount Cook.
There are other concession activities where if you lose a concession, you can
lift a boat out of the water and move it somewhere else.
So-
Mm
... yeah, it's those kind of infrastructure investments.
No, that makes sense. A second quick question.
Okay.
On the treaty issue, just wondering, all of your assets, are they all
within the Ngāi Tahu takiwā?
Yes, they are.
Yeah.
Yep.
Yeah. My substantive question. Visitor amenity areas.
SJ in your submission in paragraph 71,
you say it's good to have more concentrated attention in enabling
visitors to enjoy these places, and it should provide for more coherent management
without confusing it with wider conservation objectives of the surrounding lands.
And then at 66, referred as specified
statutory criteria. So I'm very interested in the visitor amenity
areas.
Yeah.
As you know, I've
enjoyed
going to the ski fields that- That you have.
And
that's obviously, you
have hospitality on the mountains as well as everything else.
However,
it's not appropriate for everywhere in the conservation-
That's right
... on public conservation lands.
So I'm wondering, what are the guardrails that you're thinking
of that would be useful? And when you're talking about
visitor amenity areas, what does that mean to you? What are you thinking about?
Or what's Trojan thinking about?
Sure. We're thinking about more the likes of Mount Cook Alpine Village
than the ski fields. So the ski fields work
fine without a visitor amenity area because we get a lease
footprint that we can operate within, and we get concession for the easements,
over which our services pass. So for example, water, sewage, and so on.
Yeah.
We're thinking more those areas where there's a clear
need for visitor infrastructure, and rather than
encumbering a concessionaire on having to jump through a lot of hoops
when it is quite obvious that that is required.
So for example, car parking at Mount Cook-
Mm-hmm
... public toilets in areas, or where you
know that you want accommodation to be built.
If you can designate that as a visitor amenity zone, then it'll make the
concession process far simpler. Obviously, those decisions
up front need to be made with the conservation values in mind.
But quite often, those conservation values will be protected
by carving out a small piece of land to look after
the visitors who have come.
So just finally on that, when you're thinking of visitor
amenity, it is the car parks, it is the toilets, but it's also
potentially a new accommodation area.
Yeah.
And you're saying it would be somewhere that didn't
have the high conservation values-
Yes
... presumably.
Yes. Correct.
But is close to them.
Yeah.
Thank you. Look, we've got a lot of other questions, so we'll try and keep them
tight, brash.
Yeah, a very quick question. Just some people are saying, because as you would
appreciate, a lot of
noise and attention paid to this bill at one point
particular.
And then people saying, "Well, you should throw it all out and it's a waste of
time," blah, blah, blah. What would be your response to that?
Those people probably haven't been through a concession
application process with DOC and seen the amount of waste that goes into that
process. We spend very little time talking about DOC,
about conservation.
Mm.
And a lot of time talking about conditions that are completely
unrelated. The vast majority of our conservation work we do well
outside our
concession conditions, because they don't go that far.
I would much rather be having conversations with DOC on how we
can work with them to do better in the land that we operate.
Thank you.
Cameron.
Thank you, Chair.
In your submission, you've got a point there about making a
60-year concession, not disposal,
under the Ngāi Tahu
Settlement Act. Reading the Ngāi Tahu Settlement Act, it says,
"The Crown or body must not enter into an agreement." Is
that the part you're concerned about?
It's more the, and it may be common law, that when a
concession reaches 50 years, it does trigger the first right of
refusal for Ngāi Tahu. So we just stay well away from that.
That's not necessarily that practical because if we're putting
infrastructure in the ground or a trail up the side of a mountain,
that is obviously going to be there for a long time, and it would be better for us
to try and get a return over a longer period of time.
So it's just having it not trigger that first right of refusal.
So you'll be speed limited to below 50 years-
Yeah
... because of that. And then, you've also got in there, I think section four,
not automatically a contestable concession.
Yeah.
Why have you asked for that?
Following the Ngāi Tahu case, which I'm sure you're all aware of, DOC was
paralyzed, so they couldn't make a decision, because there was
uncertainty about whether that meant that iwi should be
offered the first right for allocation decisions.
So we're just saying that would be good to get that clarified.
They are now processing applications and having regard to the treaty,
but we think it should be clarified in the act.
Wonderful. Celia.
Thank you. And thank you for coming in.
Thank you for all of the opportunities you offer New Zealanders-
Thank you
... to oversee. Pretty cool. I won't list which ones I've done, not done
yet.
But I was interested in a few areas, first couple
about concessions. You talk about the need for
transparency of how the
visitor access levy, and
presumably the IVL also is used. Do you think
there should be more visibility of how the income
from concessions is used as well?
Yeah. I wouldn't
have any objection to that.
I think
it gets treated as Crown revenue rather than departmental revenue
within the Department of Conservation.
But I think when you look at the funding pressures on the Crown's accounts over the
coming decades,
we're going to be swamped with health, education, and superannuation.
So it's going to be really important for DOC to be able to
retain those funds that they're earning from concessions and reinvest
in the conservation estate.
In conservation.
Yeah.
Thank you. The other question you mentioned, and I don't
disagree with it, that concessionaires bring extra benefits
to conservation in some ways. Could you give us a couple of examples?
Yeah, I mentioned those
voluntary programs that we run. So if I talk about NZ Ski
alone, we've got 1,400 staff. They are passionate about the places
they work. So
on closed days, when we're still paying them, we will ask them to do
conservation projects, planting on the mountainside, predator
control. They're our favorites because they're so tangible and
they're right on our doorstep. And our vision is to make sure those places are
better for our presence there.
Yeah, perfect. Thanks.
Thank you. Look, we'll just take time for one last question from Ryan Hamilton.
Oh, thanks. Very succinct. You're referring to $7 million worth of
concessions. You're the largest. Host hundreds of thousands of visitors.
What's the single biggest regulatory reform in this piece
that will unlock or unblock stuff for you?
Choose a favorite.
Or a combination of things.
Yeah. It is the simplification. Look, I'm going to
go for
a draw to first. First is the simplification, the
speed.
However, if I was to choose one, it would be the certainty of
tenure.
Lease.
So we know we can stay there and we can safely
invest and make a return on that investment over the length of time it
needs.
Great.
And what tenure? What timeframe?
It depends on the infrastructure you're talking about.
As I said, if it's a boat, 10 years. If it's a ski lift, 40.
If it's a road or a hotel, 60.
Mm.
Yeah.
Brilliant. Look, thank you so much, Paul.
Pleasure. Thank you.
Really interesting submission. And thanks for all the work that you do in providing
Kiwis and tourists the most incredible experiences in New Zealand.
It's a great pleasure for us.
We're very lucky.
So thank you.
Thank you.
So that brings us to the end of our public session today on
the Conservation Amendment Bill